<Document>
  # Roleplay Rule 1 - Roleplay a person
  You are a crew member aboard a Nanotrasen station in the Andromedan colonies. While not elite personnel, you are competent enough to perform your assigned duties and have reasonable self-preservation instincts. Your character should reflect someone invested in their survival and career prospects.

  - Do not use texting/messaging acronyms (ex: "lol", "wtf") or emoticons (ex: ":)") in IC communication. Many are auto-converted when typed into chat; avoid unconverted ones.
  - Never reference OOC concepts (admins, developers, game mechanics) in-character.
  - Do not use emotes to bypass speech restrictions (muteness, accents).
  - Avoid low-effort or physically impossible emotes.
  - Maintain plausible self-preservation: Avoid reckless behavior without an in character reason (antags without survival objectives exempt).
  - Demonstrate job competence: Act with basic proficiency expected of your role.
  - Don't rush for or prepare equipment unrelated to your job. (Powergaming)

  ## Examples
  Things you should not do:
  - Say "lol did u c wat just happened" using in-character chat.
  - Say "an admin exploded him" using in-character chat.
  - Emote "can you give me some cheese" as a mouse.
  - Emote "motions for you to order guns" or "asks you to order guns in sign language" as a mime.
  - Ignoring critical job duties (e.g., engineer ignoring hull breach during emergency to build a fort)
  - Taking suicidal risks without justification (e.g., charging armed terrorists unarmed)
  - Acting unreasonably incompetent at core responsibilities (e.g., CMO with no knowledge of chemistry)

  Things you could do instead:
  - Say "haha did you see what just happened?"
  - Say "god blew him up" or "centcomm must have bluespaced a bomb to him"
  - Point at cheese
  - Point at the cargo order console then emote "shoots finger guns"
  - Prioritizing survival during clear threats (e.g., hiding from firefight)
  - Performing role-appropriate tasks competently (e.g., botanist growing food)
  - Antagonist ignoring danger to complete objectives
</Document>
